Beverly Cassara Papers
Beverly Cassara Papers
1943-1999
Cassara, Beverly Benner.
22.75 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings, research material, personal papers, audiovisual material, printed material of the American adult educator. Includes extensive information on participatory research, volksschule (folk schools), and international and multicultural education. Organizations and institutions with a significant presence in the collection include the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), Association for Women in Development (AWID), the International Council for Adult Education (ICAE), Colby College, Highlander Research and Education Center, the University of Southern Maine, and the University of the District of Columbia. Notable individuals with a significant presence in the collection include Thelma Barer-Stein, Julius Seelye Bixler, Marcie Boucouvalas, Willard Callender, Paolo Freire, Martha Friedenthal-Haase, Peter Jarvis, Faustine Jones-Wilson, Malcolm Knowles, Volker Lühr, Helge Pross, and Matthias Wesseler.
2496129
Biographical History
Beverly Benner Cassara is an American professor of adult education, with a particular focus on participatory research, international/multicultural education, and women's education,
Beverly Cassara was born in Hanover, MA, daughter of the Reverend Guy Percy Benner and Julia Caroline Whitney Benner. She received her B.A. from Colby College in 1947 and her first job after graduation was as a news editor and broadcaster for WBET in Brockton, Massachusetts. Soon after this she married Ernest Cassara (1949) and taught in the Massachusetts schools for several years while working on her Master's degree which she received from Bridgewater State University in 1954. She and Ernest had three children: Catherine (??), Nicholas (1957), and Shirley (1962).
In 1962 Cassara was a Visiting Scholar at Cambridge University and in 1963-1964 she and her family spent a year in Churwalden, Switzerland where she was the Director of Personnel and student counselor at the Albert Schweitzer College. Returning to the United States, she worked for four years (1966-1970) as the Director of Adult Education at Goddard College, a small liberal arts college with a highly individualized approach to instruction. She continued to take graduate courses while working, and in 1970 received her Ed.D. from Boston University; one of her professors was Malcolm Knowles, with whom she became good friends.
For the next twenty years (1970-1990), Cassara's primary position was Professor of Adult Education at Federal City College (FCC) in Washington, D.C. and then at the University of the District of Columbia, created by FCC's merger with two other institutions. During these years, in addition to her regular work at FCC and later UDC, she served as Acting Director of the Institute for Continuing Education for Women (1972-1976) and as Dean of Graduate Studies (1973-1985), produced several television programs for the local NBC affiliate (1979), and taught at several other institutions including Northern Virginia Comunity College (1971-1972), Fairfax County Adult Education Program (1971), and Virginia Polytechnic (1974-1979).
In 1974 she was awarded a Fulbright Fellowship and as a result the Casssaras spent much of 1975-1976 in Berlin, Germany where Ernest guest lectured in American History while Beverly lectured at the Pädagogische Hochschule Berlin and undertook an extensive research project into women in adult education in Germany. She put serious effort into becoming fluent in German; many of her lectures were delivered in German and she maintained close professional relationships with several educators whom she met in Berlin including Helge Pross, Gerd Doerry, and Helmuth Dolff. In 1982 she returned to Germany to give a series of lectures under the auspices of the Forschungsinstitut für Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften (FIGS) at the Universität Gesamthochschule Siegen.
Cassara was also interested in adult education in third-world countries, particularly Africirca The University of the District of Columbia maintained a collegial relationship with the University of Nairobi, including doctoral student sponsoring and faculty exchange, and Cassara visited Kenya more than once and worked closely with several visiting faculty and doctoral students.
One of Cassara's projects in Washington, D.C. involved work with low-income women, and she encouraged her adult education students to become involved as part of their coursework. She directed adult education students who worked in the Jubilee Housing Project as well as a similar project at the Montana Terrace Housing Project (which resulted in a number of articles and papers). One of her students, Eve Tetaz, went on to found Life Pathways, Inc., a literacy and educational assistance organization in the D.C. area.
After retiring from UDC, she worked as an Adjunct Professor at the University of Southern Maine (1990-1995) and then founded the Cambridge Senior Volunteer Clearinghouse in Cambridge, Massachusetts. The CSVC matches seniors and other persons interested in volunteering with agencies in Cambridge and nearby communities that can utilize their skills and talents.
Ms. Cassara received a number of awards and recognitions over her career from organizations with whom or for whom she worked, including the Vermont Council for the Social Sciences (1968), the District of Columbia Public Schools (1976), and the Adult Education Association of the USA (1978). In 1978 she was named a "Woman of Achievement" by WETA in Washington, DC (the audiotape of her interview on this occasion is in the collection) and was inducted into the International Adult and Continuing Education Hall of Fame in 2003.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Beverly Cassara Papers include correspondence, writings, research material, and personal papers of the American adult educator and researcher. The collection provides an overview of her career and offers insight not only into her professional concentrations of international/multicultural adult education, participatory research, and women's education, but also into the challenges of combining a career with motherhood and some of the challenges faced by professional women in the 1970s, just as the women's rights movement was gathering momentum.
Correspondence-subject files comprises correspondence and other material relating to colleagues in adult education both in the United States (Rowena Ansbacher, Thelma Barer-Stein, Julius Seelye Bixler, Gordon Darkenwald, James Draper, William S. Griffith, Myles Horton, Faustine Jones-Wilson, Malcolm Knowles, Charlotte Morgan, John Niemi) and abroad (Gerd Doerry, Gunther Dohmen, Helmuth Dolff, Werner Düchting, Martha Friedenthal-Haase, Heribert Hinzen, Florida Karani, Peter Kinyanjui, Volker Lühr, Khalfan Mazrui, Helge Pross, Matthias Wesseler); and organizations (American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, Association for Women in Development, International Council for Adult Education, Metropolitan Washington Association of Adult and Continuing Education, Society for Participatory Research in Asia, Unitarian Universalist Association, Vermont Governor's Commission on the Status of Women). Here also is material from institutions at which Cassara was a student (Boston University, Colby College) or professor (Goddard College, Federal City College, University of the District of Columbia, University of Southern Maine) as well as from some of her former students (Cara Fulton, Eve Tetaz). Correspondence relating to some of Cassara's writings is also here, listed under the book title (American Women: The Changing Image, Adult Education in a Multicultural Society, Adult Education Through World Collaboration, "Love and the Affluent Suburban Woman," Rethinking Adult Education for Development).
Writings includes articles, book reviews, Cassara's dissertation, papers, school papers (written for both Master's and doctoral courses), the Siegen lectures (in English and German), and speeches, as well as miscellaneous material not related to adult education (Colby College alumni magazine class of 1947 columns, German language notes and translations, sermons and readings for Unitarian Universalist services, travel pieces, and so on). This series also includes the drafts, typescripts and galleys of the three books Cassara edited: Adult Education in a Multicultural Society (chapter abstracts, contributor bios, drafts of introduction and all 13 chapters, index, typescripts, galleys, published editions, and reviews/publicity), Adult Education Through World Collaboration (prospectus, chapter abstracts, contributor bios, drafts of preface, introduction and all 16 chapters, index, typescripts, galleys, published editions, and reviews/publicity), and American Women: The Changing Image (drafts, published hardcover, reviews and publicity, and a Japanese abridged edition).
Research material contains documentation related to Cassara's areas of interest or to one of her publications. Topics include the Antigonish movement, folk schools or volksschule (including a significant amount concerning the Highlander Folk School in Monteagle, Tennessee), German adult educators, Nikolai Grundtvig (a Danish folk school proponent), international studies in adult education, multicultural education, participatory research, study circles, and women's issues (including one folder on "Early 70s women's movement").
Personal papers comprises material related to Cassara's personal life. It includes address books, appointment books, awards and recognitions, clippings about her, family memorabilia, medical and dental insurance information, passports and other identity papers, resumes, "The story of 529 Webster Street" (Cassara's family reminiscences), travel souvenirs, and miscellany. Also included here are all of Cassara's personal journals, covering nearly thirty years (1966-1991). Where the journal is entirely or primarily concerned with one topic, it has been so annotated (e.g., "1975 - BC's Fulbright year in Germany"). Not all years are equally well covered, and individual entries range from several pages to a few jotted phrases.
Audiovisual material covers all videotapes, audiotapes and slides present in the collection (photographs are dispersed throughout the collection). Of particular interest are the 23 audiotapes Cassara made in 1982, interviews with German adult educators including Gerd Doerry, Helmuth Dolff, Werner Düchting, Volker Lühr, Monika Oels, and Matthias Wesseler. There are also tapes of other individuals (President Jimmy Carter, Paolo Freire, American educator Malcolm Knowles, the Finnish Minister of Education, German educator Martha Friedenthal-Haase, Anita Hill (presumably relating to the Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination hearings), and African-American professor and scholar Manning Marable. Slides include Kenya, the USSR and Finland.
Printed material comprises a variety of articles, books, brochures, clippings, fliers, magazines, newsletters, newspapers, etc, mostly on geographical areas (Africa, Eastern Europe, Germany, Hong Kong, Kenya, the Middle East, Thailand) with a few miscellaneous other topics (World Bank, minorities).
Other Formats Available
Several of the audiorecordings have been digitized. Please contact the repository listed above for more information.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Writings are subdivided by type and arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries. Research material, personal papers, audiovisual material, and printed material are arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Three books by photographer Edward Steichen, two of which are signed and inscribed to "B.B." with thanks for her assistance, were removed for separate cataloging. Beverly Cassara worked with Steichen as his secretary at the Navy Department and assisted him in the preparation of these books.
Also removed for separate cataloging was an edition of The Knight in the Panther's Skin, a medieval narrative poem from Eastern Europe which is sometimes considered Georgia's national epic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Jones-Wilson, Faustine C. (Faustine Childress), 1927-; Callender, Willard D., Jr.; Cassara, Beverly Benner.; Doerry, Gerd.; Friedenthal-Haase, Martha.; Knowles, Malcolm S. (Malcolm Shepherd), 1913-1997.; Marable, Manning, 1950-2011.; Pross, Helge, 1927-; Federal City College.; International Council for Adult Education.; University of the District of Columbia.; Adult education -- Africa.; Adult education -- Germany.; Adult education -- Research.; Adult education -- United States.; Alternative education.; Educators -- United States.; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); Highlander Research and Education Center (Knoxville, Tenn.); International studies in education.; Multicultural education.; Participant observation.; Women -- Education.; Adult education in a multicultural society.; Adult education through world collaboration.; American women: the changing image.; Audiotapes.; Book reviews.; Books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Meeting notes.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Papers (document genres); Photographs.; Research notes.; Slides (photographs); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Beverly Cassara, 1994-1999
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - 4-H Fellowship Program, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Academy for Educational Development, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education Association of the USA, See American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.
  - Adult Education Association of Virginia, See Virginia Association of Adult and Continuing Education.
  - Adult Education in a Multicultural Society, 1986-1990; undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Books: Adult Education in a Multicultural Society, as well as correspondence with individual authors.
  - Adult Education Quarterly, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education Research Conference, 1976; 1988-1990,; 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education Through World Collaboration, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Adult Learning, 1989 (Box 1)
  - African Adult Education Association, publications, printed material; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - African Association for Literacy and Adult Education
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Printed material (Box 2)
  - Alf, Herb and Sylvia, 1978; 1990,; 1997 (Box 2)
  - Allbritten, Drew, 1993 (Box 2)
  - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
    - Awards and recognitions, 1974, 1975; 1979,; 1980,; 1984,; 1986-1989 (Oversize 3)
    - Conference, Oct 1985 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1978; 1980-1994,; undated (Box 2)
    - Adult Learning article submissions, 1993; BC was editor of the "Reflections" column of Adult Learning in 1993; these are articles submitted during her tenure (Box 2)
    - Printed material, 1974; 1983-1984,; 1989-1993,; undated; newsletters, leadership roster, fliers (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, notes, undated papers, paper presented by BC, book published by AAACE Popular Education in Quebec: Strengthening Social Movements (Box 2)
  - American Society for Training and Development, 1991 (Box 2)
  - American University, 1980; program from investiture of Richard Berendzen as president; BC attended representing the Adult Education Association of the USA (Box 2)
  - American Women: The Changing Image, 1959-1962 (Box 2)
  - Americorps, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Amerika Haus, 1974-1976; 1992,; undated; Amerika Haus Berlin, Amerika Haus Frankfurt, Amerika Haus Hamburg (Box 2)
  - Amnesty International, 1988; 1993 (Box 2)
  - Amory, Cleveland, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Annual World Asembly on Adult Education (4th), See International Council for Adult Education: 1990 annual meeting (Bangkok).
  - Ansbacher, Rowena, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Asian-American Free Labor Institute, 1986; program from seminar, "Trade Union Education Techniques," at which BC presented (Box 3)
  - Aspen Institute Berlin (Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies), 1978 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1974; 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - Association for Community Based Education, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Association for Continuing Higher Education, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Association for Women in Development (AWID)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Newsletters and printed material (Box 3)
  - Atlantic Council of the United States, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Axford, Roger, 1977-1978; 1994 (Box 3)
  - Baehr, Bob and Inger, 1990-1991; includes pamphlet on the Nordic Women's Campaign against the EC, with Inger's English translation (Box 3)
  - Bangkok/Hong Kong trip, 1990; correspondence, negatives, photographs, souvenirs, travel documents, receipts, notes; 2 folders (Box 3)
    See also Personal papers: Journals: 1990 [Hong Kong/Bangkok trip].
  - Barer-Stein, Thelma, 1985; BC served on her PhD dissertation committee (Box 3)
    See also Correspondence-subject files: Adult Education in a Multicultural Society and Writings: Books: Adult Education in a Multicultural Society, chapter 9 material.
  - Barnet, Richard, undated; clipping (Box 3)
  - Barrow, Nita, 1991-1993 (Box 3)
  - Barth, Alvin, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Beacon College, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Beacon Press, See American Women: The Changing Image.
  - Bernard, Jessie, 1975; 1980 (Box 4)
  - Bersch, Gretchen
    - Correspondence, 1995-1996; includes photocopy of flier on Bersch's "Conversations on Lifelong Learning" project (Box 4)
    - Adult education class, University of Alaska, Anchorage, VHS videotape of BC's visit to class; See Audiovisual material: Adult education class, University of Alaska.
  - Bethel Area Task Force, Education Group, 1992; undated; BC was a member; clippings, booklet of Bethel area educational resources (Box 4)
  - Bixler, Julius Seelye, former President of Colby College; correspondence, clippings, two books by Bixler and other of his writings. "Pres. Bixler was my role model and my life-long friend."; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Boston University
    See also Knowles, Malcolm; Phillips, Gene; Siegle, Peter.
    - Correspondence, 1964-1970; 1994-1995,; undated (Box 4)
    - Grades, transcripts, etc (Box 4)
    - Memorabilia, 1970; Ed.D. graduation and hooding ceremony (Box 4)
  - Boucouvalas, Marcie, 1983; 1988,; 1992-1995,; undated; includes paper by MB, "Toward a Conceptualization of International Adult Education: Some Preliminary Thoughts and Reflections" (Box 4)
    See also International Associates in Adult Education, of which Ms. Boucouvalas was chair, and International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE).
  - Bown, Lalage, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Brandeis University, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Brockett, Ralph G., undated; manuscript of paper "Development and utilization of professional literature: A survey of adult education professors" (Box 4)
  - Buck, Pearl S., 1962 (Box 4)
  - Bush, George H. W., 1992 (Box 4)
  - Callender, Willard, 1989-1997; includes several papers and articles by Callender; 2 folders (Box 4)
    See also Adult Education Through World Collaboration and "Professors of Adult Education Survey on Racism and Diversity".
  - Cambridge Senior Volunteer Clearinghouse, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1976 (Box 5)
    See also Audiovisual material: [Jimmy Carter].
  - Cassara family
    Here is included all correspondence to and from BC's mother and grandmother; BC's husband Ernest and their three children Cathie, Shirley, and Nick; BC's siblings Kaye (husband Bill), Fran (husband Jack), and Karl (wife Nat). Barbara Gove may be another sister or other relative.
    - Albert Schweitzer year, 1962-1964; letters written while BC was Director of Personnel and Student Counselor at Albert Schweitzer College in Churwalden, Switzerland; a few carbons of BC's letters to various friends are included here for continuity (Box 5)
    - Later years, 1970-1995; undated (Box 5)
    - Christmas letters, 1973-1994; annual holiday letters to family and friends (Box 5)
    - Oversize card, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Chase, —, 1966; family physician (Box 5)
  - Chatham College, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Chesaro, Lina Tungo, 1982; 1987,; undated; includes paper proposal and two sections, with BC's comments (Box 5)
    For the paper that resulted from this collaboration, see Writings: Papers: The emerging role of women adult educators in Kenya.
  - Chisholm, Shirley, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Choice, 1975; 1978-1981,; 1983-1987,; 1990; BC reviewed books for this magazine for many years (Box 5)
  - Clark, Kenneth A., 1970; includes copy of Clark's paper, "A Possible Reality: A Design for the Attainment of High Academic Achievement for the Students of the Public Elementary and Junior High Schools of Washington, D.C." (Box 5)
  - Clinton, Bill, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Clinton, Hillary, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), 1981; 1986,; 1988-1994; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Cohen, William S. (U.S. Senator), 1993 (Box 5)
  - Colby College
    See also Bixler, Julius Seelye.
    - Correspondence, 1970; 1976-1977,; 1981,; 1983,; 1985,; 1988,; 1992-1997 (Box 6)
    - Memorabilia
      - Alumni magazines, 1975; 1977,; 1988,; 1992,; 1995,; 1996; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Course catalogs, 1943; 1954 (Box 6)
      - 50th reunion, class of 1947, 1997; includes text of remarks delivered by BC, "Celebrating Life" (Box 6)
      - Yearbooks, 1944; 1947 (Box 6)
      - Yearbook, 1946 (Box 8)
      - Miscellany, sticker, clipping, campus map, calendar, 1982-1983 contributions report (Box 7)
  - Colby-Sawyer College, 1977 (Box 7)
  - College of Adult and Distance Education (COADE), See Gikuhi, David.
  - Columbia University Teachers College, 1979; BC's site visit report on Ed.D. and Ph.D. programs in adult education (Box 7)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), 1976; 1986,; 1989-1994 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Study and Research in Comparative Adult Education (CSRCAE), See International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE).
  - Convergence, See International Journal of Adult Education.
  - Cosman, Bill, 1992-1993; includes draft of a chapter on prison education, intended for one of BC's books (Box 7)
    See also International Council for Adult Education: Criminal justice programme.
  - Council for Adult and Experiential Learning (CAEL), 1980 (Box 7)
  - Council of Graduate Schools (COGS), 1975; 1977,; 1978,; 1982 (Box 7)
  - Cretella, Jay, 1994; letter concerning BC's nomination for the J. Roby Kidd Award (Box 7)
  - Darkenwald, Gordon, 1974; 1977; correspondence, copy of 1974 paper by Darkenwald, "Some Effects of the 'Obvious Variable': Teacher's Race and Holding Power with Black Adult Students" (Box 7)
  - Deutscher Volkshochschul-Verband (DVV), See Dolff, Helmuth; Hinzen, Heribert; Horn, Jakob.
  - Distance education, 1992-1993; clipings, paper "Achievement motivation in distance education" (B.K. Gitau, 1985), printouts of online discussions sent to BC by Dave Ellis (Box 8)
  - District of Columbia
    - Department of Human Services, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Public Schools, Division of Adult and Continuing Education, 1976 (Box 7)
    - U.S. District Court, 1976; subpoena for civil case, Susan E. Wilson v. District of Columbia (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972; 1977,; 1985,; 1986 (Box 7)